[{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"1. The sauterelle (“so-TRELL”) was designed to target these locations, which is where satirical journals such as The Wipers Times were published. Denizens of these locations frequently used a collapsible “periscope” to stay hidden from fake “O.P. Trees.” Inhabitants of these locations exhibited the “live and let live” behavior, exemplified by the “Christmas Truce” during which men left these locations to fraternize in “no man’s land.” The mechanized tank was developed in response to the futile form of “warfare” characterized by these structures during World War I. For 10 points, barbed wire was often used to protect what defensive structures dug through battlefield terrain? ","answer":"ANSWER: trenches [accept trench warfare; prompt on the front line, the frontier, or warfronts; prompt on World War I battlefields or battlegrounds by saying “what specific locations on those battlefields?”; prompt on fortifications; prompt on ditches or other descriptive answers regarding channels dug through the ground] <European History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"2. Backbiting can occur in a ring-opening reaction to create these molecules. A “living” process can be used to create these compounds without termination. The degree of processes used to synthesize these compounds is equal to one over one minus the extent of reaction. Solutions of these molecules are described in Flory–Huggins theory. The “weight average molecular weight” over the “number average molecular weight” for these compounds is called dispersity. Ziegler–Natta catalysts are used to synthesize these molecules, and free radicals are used in chain-growth formation of these molecules. Nylon and rubber are examples of, for 10 points, what compounds made of repeating monomer units? ","answer":"ANSWER: polymers <Chemistry> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"3. In this novel, a girl smashes her fingers in a door while saying “Mean, mean, mean” to herself. A child in this novel puts a needle in a piece of bread and feeds it to his dog, who runs off in pain. Ryunosuke (“ryoo-NO-skay”) Akutagawa’s “The Spider’s Thread” is based on a parable in this novel in which a wicked woman tries to climb out of Hell on an onion. Christ returns to Earth but the church imprisons him because he guaranteed humanity free will in this novel’s “Parable of the Grand Inquisitor.” For 10 points, name this novel about Alyosha and his older siblings Dmitri and Ivan, written by Fyodor Dostoyevsky. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Brothers Karamazov [or The Karamazov Brothers or Brat’ya Karamazovy] <European Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"4. In an excerpt from this ballet, four dancers perform sixteen pas de chat (“pah duh shah”) with linked arms. Riccardo Drigo edited the original score of this ballet for the 1895 Petipa and Ivanov revival. In an oft-imitated pas de deux (“pah duh doo”) from this ballet, the ballerina performs a series of 32 fouettés (“fway-TAYS”). The protagonist of this ballet breaks the crossbow he received for his twenty-first birthday. In modern productions of this work, the same ballerina plays two roles: one dressed in white, and another in black. At a ball in this ballet, Rothbart introduces his daughter to Prince Siegfried. For 10 points, name this ballet set to music by Tchaikovsky in which Odette is cursed to turn into the title bird. ","answer":"ANSWER: Swan Lake [or Lebedínoye ózero] <Other Arts> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"5. A newspaper published by this person promised “Principle, not policy; Justice, not favors,” and was called The Revolution. This person denounced a “high-handed outrage upon my citizen’s rights” during a trial in Rochester overseen by Supreme Court Justice Ward Hill, who fined this person 100 dollars for voting in the 1872 presidential election. Carrie Chapman Catt succeeded this woman as head of the NAWSA (“N-A-W-S-A”), an organization that she founded with her longtime ally Elizabeth Cady Stanton. For 10 points, name this woman’s rights activist and architect of the 19th Amendment, who in 1979 became the first female American depicted on a U.S. coin. ","answer":"ANSWER: Susan B. Anthony <American History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"6. Mr. Yin ties Juliet to a clock tower as an homage to this director in the Season Four finale of Psych. Survivors swing clothes hangers at frenzied CGI animals in a 2010 ripoff of one of this man’s movies subtitled “Shock and Terror.” Vince Vaughn starred in Gus Van Sant’s color shot-for-shot copy of one of this man’s films, which Bernard Herrmann scored with only a string section. David Selznick produced this non-American man’s first Hollywood film, which ends with Manderley Mansion collapsing on the insane Mrs. Danvers. For 10 points, name this director who adapted Daphne du Maurier’s Rebecca to film, and created the Bates Motel for his masterpiece Psycho. ","answer":"ANSWER: Alfred Hitchcock (The film in the second sentence is Birdemic.) <CE/Geo/Other/Pop Culture> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"7. The protagonist of a novel by this author learns a belly dance from Riad Halabí (“ah-lah-BEE”) that she will perform for the man she loves most in her life. The title character of a novel by this author is conceived when a gardener bitten by a snake has sex with Consuelo. This author who created Rolf Carlé began and ended another novel with the sentence “Barrabas came to us by sea.” Blanca gives birth to Alba in a novel by this author that begins with the poisoning of Rosa the Beautiful. Clara del Valle (“VAH-yay”) marries Esteban in a novel by this author about three generations of the Trueba (“troo-AY-bah”) family. For 10 points, name this Chilean author of Eva Luna and The House of the Spirits. ","answer":"ANSWER: Isabel Allende <World/Other Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"8. A poem by Stesichorus (“steh-SICK-uh-russ”) about a battle over these creatures compares the title character’s death to a poppy shedding its petals. The eyes of these animals provide a common epithet for Hera, to whom these animals were sacred. The two-headed hound Orthrus died guarding these creatures, which were the object of Heracles’s tenth labor. Hermes tied brushwood to these creatures’ tails to hide their tracks while stealing them from Apollo. After Daedalus built a wooden one of these animals for Pasiphaë (“puh-SIFF-uh-ee”), one of them fathered a monster that was kept in the Labyrinth. For 10 points, name this animal that forms half of the Minotaur. ","answer":"ANSWER: cattle [or cows or bulls or oxen; accept the cattle of Geryon] <Mythology> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"9. This thinker’s reading of the misogynistic self-loathing Jew Otto Weininger influenced his investigation of man as a “speaking animal,” according to comments by his executor Rush Rhees (“reez”). Kimberley Cornish asserted that schoolyard interactions with this thinker in Linz ignited Hitler’s antisemitism. As an early-career advocate of logical atomism, this philosopher riffed on the title of a “Theological and Political” treatise by Baruch Spinoza for his first major work, which contains such numbered propositions as “the world is everything that is the case” and “a logical picture of facts is a thought.” For 10 points, name this philosopher of language who wrote the Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ludwig Wittgenstein <Philosophy> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"0. An equation named for these things can be solved by applying Green’s identities according to Kirchhoff’s integral theorem. In that PDE named for these entities, the second time derivative of u is proportional to the Laplacian of u. Envelopes outline these entities, which can cause beats when similar ones are combined. In a dispersion relation, omega over k is the phase velocity of these entities. The “standing” types of these entities have nodes that remain static. The LIGO (“LYE-goh”) experiment detected gravitational examples of these entities. For 10 points, name these oscillations that come in longitudinal and transverse types and have frequencies and amplitudes. ","answer":"ANSWER: waves [accept wave equation; accept standing waves; accept gravitational waves] <Physics> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"1. John Russell claimed that this scene is a “generic name for an environment in which bodily harm is done” while others “gather to watch” in works such as a triptych of figures inspired by the Furies on a red background. The central figure rests upon the net of a tesseract in a depiction of this scene by Salvador Dalí subtitled Corpus Hypercubus. Francis Bacon painted Three Studies for Figures at the Base of this scene. Diego Velázquez’s painting of this scene portrays its central figure under a sign with Greek, Latin, and Hebrew translations of the initialism INRI (“I-N-R-I”). For 10 points, name this scene in which Christ is depicted hanging on a cross. ","answer":"ANSWER: crucifixion [accept equivalents such as Christ on the cross until read] <Painting/Sculpture> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"2. Rulers of this empire referred to their territory by a term meaning “Four Parts Together.” This empire’s southern expansion halted after the Battle of the Maule (“MAO-leh”), when it clashed with the Mapuche people. Quizquiz (“kees-kees”) served as a general of this empire under Huayna Capac and helped another ruler of this empire win a civil war against his brother Huascar. That ruler of this empire, who tried to secure his freedom by filling a room with gold after being captured by Spanish forces at Cajamarca, was named Atahualpa. For 10 points, Cusco was the capital of what pre-Columbian empire conquered by Francisco Pizarro and centered in Peru? ","answer":"ANSWER: Incan Empire [accept Tawantisuyu] <World History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"3. When this variable was increased in an experiment by Norman Triplett, cyclists were found to bike faster. As this quantity grows, the Ringelmann effect worsens, as seen in experiments centered on pulling a rope. Darley and Latané (“LAH-tuh-nay”) changed this quantity between trials of an experiment in which a room slowly filled with smoke. Diffusion of responsibility increases as this variable increases, thus increasing social loafing; that process contributes to an effect magnified by this variable’s increase that is sometimes named for the Central Park murder of Kitty Genovese. For 10 points, name this quantity whose increase worsens the bystander effect, and may lead to groupthink. ","answer":"ANSWER: the number of people [or number of participants; or clear equivalents; accept population size; accept group size; prompt on number or n] <Social Science> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"4. When this novel was first published in the United States, the editor omitted its 21st and final chapter depicting the protagonist’s maturation because he thought it was “bland.” David Pelham designed the iconic “cog-eyed” man on the original cover of this novel. The author of this novel objected to including a glossary to define words like “lewdies” and “litso” from this novel’s Russian-based slang, Nadsat. The protagonist of this novel frequents the Korova Milkbar with his “droogs,” and he is conditioned to hate Beethoven’s “Glorious Ninth” after undergoing Ludovico’s technique. For 10 points, name this novel about the violent teenager Alex, by Anthony Burgess. ","answer":"ANSWER: A Clockwork Orange <British Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"5. A derivative of one of these molecules, sarcosine, may act as a marker for prostate cancer. The “branched chain” variety of this class of molecules builds up in the bodies of patients with maple syrup urine disease. Reacting an aldehyde with ammonium chloride and potassium cyanate is the first step in a synthesis of these molecules named for Adolph Strecker. Bonds between these zwitterionic molecules are characterized by phi and psi angles. These molecules include a carboxyl group and their namesake NH3 group. For 10 points, glycine is the simplest example of what building blocks of proteins? ","answer":"ANSWER: amino acids <Biology> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"6. The autopsy of one holder of this position supposedly revealed that he had a “heart the size of a peppercorn.” Two “Partition Treaties” signed in The Hague and London failed to determine who would gain this position. The Treaty of Ilbersheim effectively removed Max Emmanuel of Bavaria from consideration for this position, whose main candidates included Archduke Charles and Louis XIV’s grandson, Philip of Anjou. The Duke of Marlborough fought in an 18th-century conflict regarding the succession of this position that began when the inbred Charles II died with no heirs. For 10 points, name this still-extant position responsible for ruling over an Iberian nation. ","answer":"ANSWER: King of Spain [accept any answers regarding inhabitants of the Spanish throne] <European History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"7. At the end of a novel by this author, two elderly women watch the protagonist’s son Wilder ride his tricycle across a highway. After her briefcase is accidentally taken, Florence begins an affair with 9/11 survivor Keith Neudecker in a novel by this author. In order to treat her fear of death, Babette cheats on her husband with Willie Mink to obtain the drug Dylar in a novel by this author. This author of Falling Man created the waste management executive Nick Shay and his wife Marian in the novel Underworld. An “Airborne Toxic Event” frightens Hitler Studies professor Jack Gladney in a novel by this author. For 10 points, name this author of White Noise. ","answer":"ANSWER: Don DeLillo [or Donald Richard DeLillo] <American Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"8. At the meal that typically follows this ritual, lines known as the nodeh leshimcha (“no-DEH leh-sheem-KHA”) are added to the ordinary birkat hamazon (“beer-COT ha-ma-ZONE”) prayers. An uncommon part of this ritual, the metzitzah (“meh-tsee-TSAH”), has fallen out of favor due to health concerns. In this ritual, the sandek (“SAHN-duck”) typically sits next to an empty chair intended for the prophet Elijah. As per Genesis 17, Abraham was the first person to undergo this ritual, which constituted the original covenant with God. In traditional Judaism, a mohel (“MOY-ull”) typically performs this ritual upon an infant once they reach eight days of age. For 10 points, name this practice in which a male’s foreskin is removed. ","answer":"ANSWER: circumcision [accept bris or brit milah] <Religion> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"9. This mathematician wrote a treatise about a puzzle similar to tangrams whose name means “battle of the bones.” This man’s namesake property holds for the reals, as for any two real numbers x and y, there exists an integer n such that n times x is greater than y. This mathematician used a number system of “myriads” to calculate the amount of sand grains that could fit in the universe in “The Sand Reckoner.” This man approximated pi by inscribing a circle inside polygons of increasing number of sides, a technique known as the “method of exhaustion.” For 10 points, name this Greek mathematician from Syracuse who upon discovering his namesake principle shouted “Eureka!” ","answer":"ANSWER: Archimedes of Syracuse <Other Science> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"0. Dmitri Shostakovich wrote his short cheerful second piece in this genre for his son Maxim’s 19th birthday. Two descending horn motifs open a piece in this genre premiered by Hans von Bülow after it was rejected by the dedicatee; that was Tchaikovsky’s first piece in this genre. Another piece in this genre was dedicated to Nikolai Dahl, the composer’s hypnotherapist. Vladimir Horowitz was the first to record Rachmaninoff’s third piece of this type, whose difficulty stems in part from chords written for the composer’s massive hands. For 10 points, name this genre of orchestral pieces featuring a keyboard instrument. ","answer":"ANSWER: piano concerto [prompt on concerto; prompt on PC] <Classical Music> Bonuses "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Dance and music accompany Ntozake Shange’s (“EN-toh-zah-kee SHON-gay’s”) monologue “no more love poems #2,” performed by a character named for this color. This color titles a novel whose protagonist writes letters to God and falls in love with Shug Avery. ","answer":"ANSWER: purple [accept the Lady in Purple or The Color Purple] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Letters and photographs are used throughout Theresa Cha’s “auto-ethnographic” novel Dictee, which is divided into nine parts based on this group. Sor Juana (“WAH-nah”) is often known as the “tenth” one of these Greek goddesses of the arts. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Muses [accept “The Tenth Muse”] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] In Claudia Rankine’s (“RANK-in’s”) book Citizen, a photograph depicting “smiling blond goodness” concludes a chapter on this activity. In another novel, Charles Tavis works at an academy for this activity founded by Hal’s father James. ","answer":"ANSWER: tennis [prompt on sports] (The novel is Infinite Jest.) <World/Other Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this string instrument featured in Joaquín (“wah-KEEN”) Rodrigo’s Concierto de Aranjuez (“ah-rahn-WEZZ”). Mario Castelnuovo-Tedesco and Francisco Tárrega primarily wrote for this instrument, an electric version of which was created by Les Paul (“less Paul”). ","answer":"ANSWER: guitar "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] A modified guitar with thinner tops is used for this genre of music, whose forms are called palos. Dancers to this music sometimes use castanets. ","answer":"ANSWER: flamenco "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This composer wrote a set of twelve etudes for the guitar virtuoso Andrés Segovia and five guitar preludes for his wife Arminda. The first of this composer’s Chôros (“SHOW-roos”) is scored for guitar. ","answer":"ANSWER: Heitor Villa-Lobos <Classical Music> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name these agglomerations of gas, dust, or other matter that orbit a star in the shape of a torus or ring. ","answer":"ANSWER: circumstellar disks [accept debris disk or transition disk or protoplanetary disk or accretion disk] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This circumstellar disk located in our solar system extends outward from the orbit of Neptune and contains asteroids, short-period comets, and dwarf planets such as Pluto. ","answer":"ANSWER: Kuiper belt [or Edgeworth–Kuiper belt] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] These objects are considered “classical” Kuiper belt objects and are often contrasted with “resonant” plutinos. These objects are named for the provisional designation of Albion, the first of them to be discovered. ","answer":"ANSWER: cubewanos (“kyoo-bee-WUN-ohs”) <Other Science> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this linguistic subfield whose subjects include the use of affixes in word formation. This subfield studies the internal structure of words. ","answer":"ANSWER: morphology "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Jean Berko Gleason’s “wug test” studied which morpheme children would add to the made-up word “wug” to give it this property. This property is contrasted with the singular and, in some languages, the dual. ","answer":"ANSWER: plural "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Fusional languages such as English often use just one morpheme to indicate a number of grammatical features, so they apply this type of inflection, which is specific to adjectives and nouns, but not verbs. ","answer":"ANSWER: declension [or word forms like declining] <Social Science> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this chapter in which a group of black boys fight each other while blindfolded and later attempt to collect coins from an electrified rug. You may also give the novel and chapter number. ","answer":"ANSWER: “Battle Royal” [accept the first chapter of Invisible Man or the opening chapter of Invisible Man; do not accept answers that use “The Invisible Man” in place of “Invisible Man”] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This author used his separately-published story “Battle Royal” as the first chapter of his novel Invisible Man. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ralph Ellison [or Ralph Waldo Ellison] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Ellison calls his “Battle Royal” scene “a ritual in preservation of caste lines” in this critical essay collection, which discusses how he began writing Invisible Man. ","answer":"ANSWER: Shadow and Act <American Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] As the second guru, Angad served as the spiritual leader of this religion that originated in the Punjab. The khalsa, this religion’s community of believers, are expected to always carry a set of items known as the “Five K’s.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Sikhism [accept Sikkhī] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Guru Angad is traditionally credited with inventing this writing style derived from earlier Sharada scripts. Printings of the Guru Granth Sahib (“grunt SAH-hib”) always use this script, whose name reflects its holy origins. ","answer":"ANSWER: Gurmukhī (“gurr-MOO-kee”) [prompt on Punjabi script; do not accept or prompt on “Shahmukhi”] (The term is often translated as “from the mouth of the Guru.”) "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] While Guru Nanak began the first of these institutions, Angad spread them across the lands. Sevadars provide free vegetarian meals to all visitors as part of these communal Sikh kitchens. ","answer":"ANSWER: langars [prompt on gurdwaras or Sikh temples] <Religion> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"6. ","answer":"ANSWER: Republic of Texas "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This man led Texan forces to victory at San Jacinto. This former Tennessee governor became governor of Texas in 1859, but was forced from office when the state seceded. ","answer":"ANSWER: Samuel Houston "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This “Father of Texas” organized the “Old Three Hundred,” the first American families to settle in the region. He lost to Houston in the republic’s first presidential election. ","answer":"ANSWER: Stephen F. Austin [or Stephen Fuller Austin] <American History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this disease whose examples include mesothelioma and leukemia. ","answer":"ANSWER: cancer [accept specific types of cancer] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This scientist observed that cancer cells perform glycolysis at ten times the rate of cells in non-cancerous tissue, in an effect now named for him. ","answer":"ANSWER: Otto Warburg "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] An “inducible factor” named for this condition can regulate the Warburg effect. This condition, caused by inadequate oxygen supply, stimulates VEGF and erythropoietin (“eh-RITH-ro-POY-uh-tin”) production. ","answer":"ANSWER: hypoxia [or hypoxia-inducible factor-1; or HIF-1] <Biology> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this family. A company owned by and named after this family is headquartered in a brick building with a Great Workroom featuring dendriform columns reminiscent of lily pads. ","answer":"ANSWER: Johnson [accept S. C. Johnson & Son or Johnson Wax] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This architect designed the Johnson Wax Headquarters and Wingspread, as well as houses like Fallingwater and the Robie House. This American architect of many Usonian houses pioneered the Prairie School of architecture. ","answer":"ANSWER: Frank Lloyd Wright "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Another Wisconsin building by Wright was his home and studio, which he gave this name. The first building of this name was burned down, but Wright rebuilt it, in addition to a house called “[this name] West” in Arizona. ","answer":"ANSWER: Taliesin (“tall-YES-sin”) [accept Taliesin II or Taliesin North or Taliesin East or Taliesin West] <Other Arts> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this secessionist force that killed Ranasinghe Premadasa (“RAH-nuh-SING-huh prem-uh-DAH-suh”) and other Sinhalese leaders during a long-running South Asian civil war. ","answer":"ANSWER: Tamil Tigers [or the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam; or LTTE; prompt on Tigers or Liberation Tigers] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] The Tamil Tigers fought to form a separate state in this island country southeast of India. This island was ruled as the British colony of Ceylon (“say-LON”). ","answer":"ANSWER: Sri Lanka "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] In 1991, a member of the Tigers assassinated this Indian prime minister in response to his deployment of Indian peacekeepers to Sri Lanka. ","answer":"ANSWER: Rajiv Gandhi [prompt on Gandhi] <World History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name these beings. They are exported all over the world to become slaves for humanity but ultimately declare war when humans are unwilling to grant them rights. ","answer":"ANSWER: newts [or salamanders] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] The newts declare war on humanity in The War with the Newts, a novel by this Czech science fiction writer. He also wrote the play R.U.R. ","answer":"ANSWER: Karel Čapek (“CHAH-peck”) "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Karel Čapek’s R.U.R. introduced the term for these machines. In the works of Isaac Asimov, these machines often have “positronic brains.” ","answer":"ANSWER: robots [accept Rossum’s Universal Robots; do not accept or prompt on synonyms such as “androids”] <European Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this phenomenon that was first observed by Cronin and Fitch in kaon (“KAY-on”) decay. This phenomenon is a deviation from the product of two symmetries. ","answer":"ANSWER: CP violation [or charge conjugation-parity symmetry violation] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Direct evidence of CP violation was first observed at the Super Proton Synchrotron, or SPS, which also discovered this group of particles that is responsible for propagating the weak nuclear force. ","answer":"ANSWER: W and Z bosons [accept W+, W–, and Z0 bosons; accept in any order] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This organization houses the SPS and includes other experiments, such as ALICE and ATLAS, in the particle-smashing LHC, or Large Hadron Collider. ","answer":"ANSWER: CERN [or European Organization for Nuclear Research or Organisation européenne pour la recherche nucléaire] <Physics> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this 2001 film in which the American Mia Thermopolis becomes the heir to Genovia. This film was the first leading role for a young Anne Hathaway. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Princess Diaries "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] In The Devil Wears Prada, Hathaway’s character Andy is charged by this actress’s character Miranda Priestly to find an unpublished Harry Potter book. This actress asked for “money, money, money” as Donna in Mamma Mia!. ","answer":"ANSWER: Meryl Streep [or Mary Louise Streep] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] In Hathaway’s role as this character, she first appears as a maid stealing Martha’s pearl necklace. While playing this character in another film, Michelle Pfeiffer scratches out a neon sign to read “Hell Here” after being thrown out of a window by Max Schreck. ","answer":"ANSWER: Catwoman [or Selina Kyle] <CE/Geo/Other/Pop Culture> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"5. ","answer":"ANSWER: Tomáš Garrigue Masaryk "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Masaryk was the first president of this no-longer existent country in Central Europe. This country’s name is a portmanteau of two modern-day countries whose capitals are Prague and Bratislava. ","answer":"ANSWER: Czechoslovakia [do not accept or prompt on “Czechia,” “Czech Republic,” or “Slovakia”] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Both Czechoslovakia’s 1989 revolution and its subsequent split into two countries are often named for this substance, referencing the peaceful nature that characterized the transition. ","answer":"ANSWER: velvet [accept the Velvet Revolution or the Velvet Divorce] <European History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this king of England who was supported by Sir John Suckling, Thomas Carew (“carry”), and other Cavalier poets during the English Civil War. ","answer":"ANSWER: Charles I [prompt on Charles] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This Cavalier wrote “This day is yours, Great CHARLES!” in a poem celebrating Charles’s victory at Leicester (“LESS-ter”). He included the poem “Corinna’s Going A-Maying” in his collection Hesperides. ","answer":"ANSWER: Robert Herrick "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This other supporter of Charles was incarcerated in Gatehouse Prison after the English Civil War, leading him to pen the lines, “Stone Walls do not a Prison make / Nor Iron bars a Cage” in his poem “To Althea, from Prison.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Richard Lovelace <British Literature> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this loa who is typically depicted as an old man with a crutch. He is said to preside over crossroads. ","answer":"ANSWER: Papa Legba "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Papa Legba is the equivalent to the Yoruba (“YO-roo-ba”) trickster deity Eṣu-Elegbara (“EH-shoo EH-leg-BA-ra”), who is in turn conflated with this figure from Christian mythology. This demon rules over Hell. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Devil [or Satan or Lucifer] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Eṣu-Elegbara is said to be accompanied by this animal, who takes on the role of Eṣu in much of Afro-American folklore. In another myth system, one of these animals tries to eat the sun because he thinks it’s a mango. ","answer":"ANSWER: monkey [accept the signifyin’ monkey or signifying monkey] (The second clue is about Hanuman.) <Mythology> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this painting currently on display at the Mauritshuis (“MAO-rits-house”) in The Hague, whose subject wears an oriental turban and robe along with the title accessory. ","answer":"ANSWER: Girl with a Pearl Earring [or Meisje met de parel; or Girl’s Face] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Girl with a Pearl Earring was painted by this artist. The realism of this Dutch Golden Age painter’s works, such as The Music Lesson and The Love Letter, has led to speculation that he used a camera obscura. ","answer":"ANSWER: Johannes Vermeer [or Jan Vermeer] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This female painter was also active during the Dutch Golden Age. All of her works, which include The Proposition and Merry Trio, were misattributed to Frans Hals until the late 19th century. ","answer":"ANSWER: Judith Leyster <Painting/Sculpture> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] By stating that “purple is the finest burial shroud,” Empress Theodora dissuaded this husband of hers from fleeing during the Nika Riots. This Byzantine emperor proceeded to commission the extant version of the Hagia Sophia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Justinian I [or Justinian the Great; accept Flavius Petrus Sabbatius Iustinianus Augustus; prompt on Justinian or Ioustinianós; do not accept or prompt on “Justin”] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Before securing power by blinding her son Constantine VI, Empress Irene called the Second Council of Nicaea to reverse this policy, which banned the use of namesake religious images in Orthodox churches. ","answer":"ANSWER: Byzantine iconoclasm [accept Eikonomachía; prompt on descriptive answers indicating the ban on or rejection of religious icons] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Shortly after being exiled by her brother John II, this historian described the effects of the First Crusade upon the Byzantine Empire in an account of the reign of her father Alexios I, the Alexiad. ","answer":"ANSWER: Anna Komnene [or Anna Comnena] <European History> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this transition metal that is found in the Jones reagent and stainless steel. This metal’s chemical symbol is Cr. ","answer":"ANSWER: chromium "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This element and chromium are found in the mineral barbertonite. This metal is found with silicon in talc, and it and calcium are bound to carbonate in dolomite. ","answer":"ANSWER: magnesium [or Mg] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This compound is often in a heptahydrate form. Its anhydrous form can be used as a drying agent, and it consists of magnesium sulfate. ","answer":"ANSWER: Epsom salt [or epsomite] <Chemistry> "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Name this philosophical position whose hard form denies the existence of free will. It asserts that all actions are at least somewhat pre-ordained. ","answer":"ANSWER: causal determinism [or word forms; accept hard determinism or soft determinism] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] Due to the rise of quantum mechanics, Sir Arthur Eddington asserted that this indeterministic phenomenon really exists, contra Einstein’s insistence that “God does not play dice with the universe.” ","answer":"ANSWER: chance [or probability; or fortune; or luck; prompt on randomness] "},{"tournament":"2019 ACF Fall ","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","question":"[10] This earlier thinker coined the term tychism (“TYKE-ism”) to describe a belief in indeterminate chance. This American rejected the methods of tenacity for scientific thinking in “The Fixation of Belief.” ","answer":"ANSWER: C. S. Peirce (“purse”) [or Charles Sanders Peirce] <Philosophy>"}]
